Thorne collection of Elias Boudinot, 1734-1924 (bulk 1777-1819 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Thorne Collection of Elias Boudinot
1734-1924
1777-1819
C0001
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
3 linear feet 4 boxes
Boudinot, Elias, 1740-1821.
Elias Boudinot was an American lawyer and public official who represented New Jersey in the Continental Congress. This collection consists of correspondence, documents, and printed material relating to Boudinot and his family, collected by Langdon K. Thorne.
Elias Boudinot was an American lawyer and public official who represented New Jersey in the Continental Congress. Born in Philadelphia in 1740, Boudinot became a lawyer in 1760. At the onset of the American Revolution, he became a member of the Revolutionary Party although he was a conservative Whig. He served as deputy in the New Jersey provincial assembly and then as a New Jersey representative in the Continental Congress. He later served as a member of the House of Representatives from 1789 to 1795 before becoming director of the U.S. Mint from 1795 to 1805. Boudinot died in 1821.
The collection consists of correspondence, documents, and printed material relating to Elias Boudinot and the Boudinot family, collected by Langdon K. Thorne. Much of Boudinot's correspondence is addressed to his wife, Hannah, sister of Richard Stockton, while he is traveling with the Continental Army as commissary-general of prisoners (1777-1778); other letters deal more directly with his prisoners-of-war work, and there are many to his brother Elisha, covering (1777-1819) the whole range of Boudinot's public service: New Jersey member of the Continental Congress (1781-1783), president of that body (1782-1783), member of the National House of Representatives (1789-1795), director of the U.S. Mint (1795-1805), and founding member and first president of the American Bible Society (1816).
In addition, there are Boudinot's personal copy of a broadside of resolutions (1776-1777) relating to the Commissary of Prisoners Department and a copy of his proclamation (24 June 1783) as president of Congress moving it to Princeton. Among papers of others in the collection are Loyalist surgeon Uzal Johnson's journal (5 March 1780 to 6 March 1781), including accounts of the battle of King's Mountain and other military movements in and around Charleston, South Carolina, while serving under General Patterson in the 71st Regiment of Light Infantry, and a bound volume of recipes belonging to Mrs. C. Boudinot.
Collection is open for research use.
Collected by Langdon K. Thorne. Received through M. Knw Knoedler and Co. in 1953.
Johnson, Uzal, 1757?-1827 -- Notebooks, sketchbooks, etc.; Boudinot, Elisha, 1749-1819.; Thorne, Langdon K.; Cookery, American -- 18th century.; Husband and wife -- United States -- 18th century.; King's Mountain, Battle of, 1780 -- Personal narratives.; Prisoners of war -- United States -- 18th century.; New Jersey -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; South Carolina -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Prisoners and Prisons.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Prisoners, Exchange of.; United States -- History, Military -- To 1900.; Broadsides -- United States -- 18th century.; Journals -- United States -- 18th century.; Recipes -- United States -- 18th century.; American history/Revolution; Publishing history
- Series 1: Boudinot, Elias: Correspondence, 1772-1819; 14 folders
  Consists of family correspondence, letter books, and other correspondence from and to Elias Boudinot, spanning the years 1772-1819. Notable correspondents include Benjamin Franklin and George Washington. The series also includes a group of letters pertaining to prisoners of war, 1777-1779.
  Letters to Mrs. Elias Boudinot (Hannah Stockton), Letters regarding prisoners-of-war, Letters by E.B. to Elisha Boudinot [22], E.B. to Elisha Boudinot [26], E.B. to Elisha Boudinot [20], and E.G. to Elisha Boudinot [21]. Followed by an alphabetical run of individual letters and includes a Letterbook of Elias Boudinot.
  - Letters to Mrs. Elias Boudinot (Hannah Stockton), 1777 July 2-1779 March 29; 1 folder
    - Camp, New Windsor, 1777 July 2; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Potts Grove, 1777 September 23; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Camp near Schuylkill, 1777 September 23; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Camp White Marsh, 1777 November 21; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Green Park, 1777 November 30; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Camp, 1778 April 22; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Camp, 1778 June 7; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Philadelphia, 1778 June 10; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Camp, 1778 June 11; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Camp, 1778 June 13; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Philadephia, 1778 June 20; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Coryells Ferry, 1778 June 22; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Philadelphia, 1778 July 7; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Philadelphia, 1778 July 9; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Princeton, 1778 August 8; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Philadelphia, 1778 August 17; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Philadelphia, 1779 March 20; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Philadelphia, 1779 March 29; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Letters regarding prisoners-of-war, 1777 April 24-1779 December 24; 1 folder
    - ALS by Nathaniel Scudder, undated; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Col. Robt. Harrison, undated; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Jos. Loring for Commissioner Lewis Pintard, 1777 April 24; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Lewis Pintard, 1777 June 9; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Jos. Loring for Commissioner Lewis Pintard, 1777 July 4; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Lewis Pintard, 1777 August 2; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Gen. Wadsworth, 1777 November 5; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Robt. Hooper, Jr, 1777 December 24; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Robt. Hooper, Jr, 1777 December; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Charles Pettet, 1778 January 1; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Jos. Loring for Commissioner Lewis Pintard, 1778 January 20; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by E.B. to George Washington, 1778 March 2; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - AN [from E.B.], 1778 March 19; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by E.B. to John Winslow, 1778 April 17; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Jos. Loring for Commissioner Lewis Pintard, 1778 April 22; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - AN Obligation by [E.B.], 1778 May 6; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - AN to Ezekiel Williams, 1778 May 6; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS to Col. Hamilton by Jos. Loring for Commissioner Lewis Pintard, 1978 June 5; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Jos. Loring for Commissioner Lewis Pintard, 1778 June 17; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by James Dirk to Elisha Boudinot, 1779 January 24; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by James Dirk to [Elisha Boudinot], 1779 February 6; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Col. Beatty to [Elisha Boudinot], 1779 June 28; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS by Col. Beatty to [Elisha Boudinot], 1779 December 24; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - AN [fragment], undated; portion of 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Letterbook of Elias Boudinot, 134 pp., 1772-1786; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Letters by E.B. to Elisha Boudinot [22], 1778-1796; 1 folder
    - Valley Forge, 1778 March 21; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Valley Forge, 1778 March 27; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1781 August 12; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Baskinridge, 1781 December 25; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1782 February 15; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1782 February 20; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1782 February 26; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1782 March 19; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1782 December 24; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1783 March 29; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1783 April 16; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1783 June 23; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1791 March 13; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1791 March 15; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1792 March 20; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1792 March 29; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia, 1794 February 20; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Rosehill, 1796 February 4; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Rosehill, 1796 February 17; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Rosehill, 1796 May 13; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Rosehill, 1796 June 22; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - U.S. Mint, 1796 November 28; portion of 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - E.B. to Elisha Boudinot [26], 1797-1801; 1 folder
    - Philadelphia, 1797 January 11; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Philadelphia, 1797 January 22; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Philadelphia, 1797 February 4; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Philadelphia, 1797 July 11; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1797 August 2; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1797 August 21; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - U.S. Mint, 1797 August 28; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1797 August 30; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1797 September 4; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1797 September 6; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1797 September 14; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1797 November 2; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1797 December 23; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1797 December 11; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Philadelphia, 1798 February 8; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1798 June 12; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1799 June 5; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1799 August 23; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Philadelphia, 1800 January 31; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1800 July 22; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Philadelphia, 1800 December 22; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Philadelphia, 1801 January 7; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Burlington, 1801 January 19; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Philadelphia, 1801 January 28; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Philadelphia, 1801 February 19; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Rosehill, 1801 June 13; portion of 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - E.B. to Elisha Boudinot [20], 1802-1811; 1 folder
    - Philadelphia, 1802 January 12; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Rosehill, 1802 July 13; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Rosehill, 1802 July 21; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Rosehill, 1802 August 23; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Rosehill, 1803 August 8; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Philadelphia, 1803 December 16; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Philadelphia, 1803 December 27; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Rosehill, 1804 November 30; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Rosehill, 1804 December 17; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Burlington, 1805 November 27; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Burlington, 1805 December 2; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Burlington, 1807 January 9; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Burlington, 1808 January 10; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Burlington, 1808 March 19; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Burlington, 1808 July 11; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Boston, 1809 July 22; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Boston, 1809 August 9; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Burlington, 1809 November 20; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Burlington, 1810 April 30; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Burlington, 1811 March 8; portion of 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - E.G. to Elisha Boudinot [21], 1812-1819; 1 folder
    - Burlington, 1812 February 3; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1812 February 15; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1814 July 30; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Princeton, 1814 October 24; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1815 January 24; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1815 March 8; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1816 May 10; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1816 July 29; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1816 October 12; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1816 November 7; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1817 February 17; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1819 February 8; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1819 February 1; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1819 February 16; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1819 February 26; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1819 April 19; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1819 June 19; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1819 July 6; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Burlington, 1819 August 8; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Philadelphia, undated; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - [fragments], undated; portion of 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - ALS to Rachel Bradford Boudinot [2], 1797-1799; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - AL to Jacob Burnet, 1809 October 15; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - ALS to Elihu Chauncey, 1819 September 26; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - ALS to Jonathan Dayton, 1801 June 13; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - ALs to Benjamin Franklin, 1783 September 9; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - ALS by Wm. Peartree Smith, 1778 July 23; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - AL [fragment] to George Washington, undated; 1 folder (Folder 14)
- Series 2: Boudinot, Elias: Documents, 1783 June 24-1818 January 1; 2 folders
  This series consists of two items pertaining to the mutiny of armed soldiers, 1783, and a power of attorney to Charles Shippen, 1818.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Re: mutiny of armed soldiers [proclamation], 1783 June 24; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Power of attorney to Charles Shippen, 1818 January 1; 1 folder (Folder 16)
- Series 3: Printed Documents and Miscellaneous Items, 1767 March 4-1969 January 19; 30 folders
  Consists of property documents in Philadelphia, circa 1788, as well as genealogical data for the Kip and Boudinot families, circa 1801. This series also includes articles regarding Elias Boudinot and his contemporaries, written during the years 1894-1916.
  Not arranged according to any arrangement scheme.
  - ALsS by Boudinot Keith to Aunt Jennie [2], 1908; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Clipping: "Invocation," initialed "E.L.B.", undated; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Deed from William Boudinot to William Keith for property in Philadelphia, 1969 January 19; portion of 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Patent of William Keith or property in Philadelphia, 1788 April 8; portion of 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Deed of Joseph Wilson for property in Philadelphia, undated; portion of 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Receipt to Dr. Samuel Ormes for contribution to the Pennsylvania Hospital, 1767 March 4; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Boudinot, Elias. Journal of Events in the Revolution (Phila.: Bourquin, 1894), 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Boudinot, Richard Stockton: photograph by Sully, undated; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - "Washington's Birthday," AMS, poem, undated; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Minutes of Meeting of the City Club [ Evening Post], 1892 December 16; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - "The Huguenots of Canterbury," AMs, 1 p., TMs, 11 pp., dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Boudinot, Julia: Calling card photograph, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Photograph and tintype of a small boy (unidentified), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Information relating to portraits of Washington and his officers, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Silver teapot (enlarged photograph), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Washington centennial catalog, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Boudinot, Elias: booklist for Chestnut Hill, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Broadside: Resolution of Commissary General of Prisoners, 1776 May 21; 1 folder (Folder 16)
  - Adams, Rev. W. Old Man's Home (New York: Gen. Protestant Episcopal S.S. Union, 1847), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  - Ritchie, A. H.: Print of engraving of Washington and his generals, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous data on Huguenot history, dates not examined; 9 items (Folder 19)
  - Massachusetts Bay Colonial Offices: unsigned, undated; 9 pp. (Folder 20)
  - Keith, Charles: genealogical data of various families connected with the Boudinot family, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 21)
  - Fly leaf/title page from New Testament with genealogical data on the Kip family, 1801; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  - Clippings related to the Boudinot family, 1912; 1 folder (Folder 23)
  - Oliver and Gallaudet families: genealogies, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 24)
  - Washington, George: copies of excerpts from his papers, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 25)
  - Notes on Huguenet history, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 26)
  - Prescription: signed "R.Hart", undated; 1 folder (Folder 27)
  - Atterbury, Rev. W. Wallace, "Elias Boudinot: Reminiscences of the American Revolution,", 1894; 1 folder (Folder 28)
  - Delafield, Maturin "William Smith", 1881; 1 folder (Folder 29)
  - Russell, Charles Howland. "The Declaration of Independence", 1916; 1 folder (Folder 30)
- Series 4: Papers of Other Persons, 1734 May 13-1818 March 2; 14 folders
  Consists of correspondence from contemporaries of Elias Boudinot, mainly correspondence to or from his family members.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Boudinot, Elisha (nephew): ALS to Elisha B. (uncle), 1808 October 2; portion of 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Boudinot, Elisha, 1770-1796 September 16; portion of 5 folders
    - Notes of Cases in Practice, 1770; 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - ALS to Nicholas Law, 1796 July 10; 1 folder (Folder 3)
    - ALS to Lewis Pintard, 1780 January 9; 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - ALS to Col. Benjamin Walker, 1796 September 16; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Boudinot, Hannah Stockton: cookbook, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Bryant, William: ALS to Samuel Storke, 1734 May 13; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Hasard, Eben: ALS to Elisha Boudinot, 1785 September 26; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Johnson, Uzal: war diary, 1780-1781; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - King, Joseph: ALS to William Hall, 1792 May 25; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Rush, Mrs. Julia (Stockton): ALS to Hannah Boudinot, undated; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Stockton, William: ALS to Elias E. Boudinot, circa 1818 March 2; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Tichenor, Isaac [Govenor of Vt.]: ALS to Elisha Boudinot, 1790 February 20; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Washington, George: ALS to Elisha Boudinot, 1783 May 10; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - A. B. Durand Engravings of Elias Boudinot, 1825; AM 15087; 1 folder (Folder 1)
    2 copies.
  - Facsimiles of Proclamations, 1783; AM 15087; 1 folder (Folder 2)
- 32101040678888 (Box 1)
- 32101040678896 (Box 2)
- 32101040678904 (Box 3)
- 32101080521071 (Box 4)